创世之初 冥冥之中
In the beginning, there was darkness,
随着一声爆炸
and then, bang--
诞生了无尽膨胀的
giving birth to an endless expanding existence
时间 空间和物质
of time, space, and matter.
每一天 新的发现都在揭秘这个诡异
Every day, new discoveries are unlocking the mysterious,
震撼 神秘莫测的
the mind-blowing, the deadly secrets
地方 - 我们所谓的《宇宙》
of a place we call "The Universe."
能量 - 终极星系变形者
Energy-- the ultimate galactic transformer,
永恒地从一种形式变为另一种形式
forever morphing from one form to another.
它驱动我们的星球
It powers our planet
以及宇宙间的万物
and everything else in the universe.
但它到底是什么？
But what exactly is it?
它究竟来自哪里？
Where did it all come from?
我们如何获得更多？
And how do we get more?
能量既不能创造也不能消灭
Energy can be neither created nor destroyed.
它只能从一种形态转换成另一种形态
It can only be transformed from one type to another.
这种转换有时会在黑洞这样的天体中变得很极端
This transformation sometimes goes to the extremes in objects like black holes.
未来文明能够利用那种能量么？
Could a future civilization harness that power?
多么利索的办法 既扔掉了垃圾
What a neat way to get rid of your garbage
同时又解决了你的能源危机
and solve your energy crisis, all at the same time.
要是我们宇宙间的能量最后转移到了别的地方 咋办呢？
And what if our universe's energy was transferred to another place in time?
要是有通道打通了平行宇宙
What if a passageway opens up to a parallel universe
流走了一些能量 又当如何呢？
and bleeds off some of that energy?
生命将无法承受
Life wouldn't be able to withstand that.
这是能量的故事
This is the story of energy,
从你自家后院的大爆炸开始讲起
from the Big Bang to your own backyard.
为你的爱车充足能量 随我们寻踪
Charge up your engines as we follow the trail
宇宙间的极端能量
of extreme energy in the universe.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://www.hdcmct.com
影片压制:暮云春树  字幕来源：HDC字幕组 调校：晴天 招募Q号: 76846146
历史频道 - 宇宙 第4季第12集 极端能量
The History Channel - The Universe s04e12 Extreme Energy
能量是宇宙变色龙
Energy is a cosmic chameleon.
它驱动着我们的宇宙千变万化
It drives our universe by constantly changing form.
它推动了加速
It powers acceleration,
扩张
expansion,
天地大冲撞
and apocalyptic impacts.
我们宇宙间的一切就是能量
Everything in our universe is energy.
你是能量 树木是能量
You're energy, trees are energy,
尘土是能量
the dirt is energy,
甚至虚无的星际也是能量
and even the empty space between the stars is energy.
但所有这些永恒变化的能量都来自何方呢？
But where does all this ever-changing energy come from?
我们终日所见的周围的所有能量
All of the energy we see around us every day
其实都来自宇宙的诞生的那一刻
actually comes from the very beginning of the universe,
数十亿年之前
billions of years ago.
你在高速公路上看到的车祸
When you see a car accident on the highway,
那是个充满能量的事件
that's a very energetic event.
汽车受损 发出巨响
Cars get mangled. There's a big noise.
然而能量又来自何方呢？
But where did the energy come from?
原来 能量来自两车相撞前的动能
Well, the energy comes from the energy of motion of the two cars before they crash.
那么汽车的能量又是从哪里来的呢？
But where do the cars get their energy?
来自汽油 化石燃料
From gas, a fossil fuel
其能量来自生长在数百万年前的植物
that gets its energy from plant life that was living millions of years ago,
植物从太阳获得能量
plant life that got its energy from the Sun,
而太阳的能量又是来自其核心的核反应
which gets its energy from nuclear reactions inside the core.
那些核反应的能量
Those nuclear reactions get their energy
来自大爆炸时所产生粒子
from the particles that were created at the time of the Big Bang.
我们周围的所有种种形式的能量
All the many forms of energy we see around us
都来自大爆炸 -
come from the Big Bang
宇宙诞生的那一刻
the beginning of the universe.
宇宙间所有物质和能量的起源
The origin of all the matter and energy in the universe
实际上就是大爆炸 -
is really the Big Bang,
宇宙自身的创建
the creation of the universe itself.
现在我们认为 事实上 大爆炸
Now we think that, in fact, the Big Bang
是极小的空间突然扩张到极大的空间
was the sudden expansion of a very small amount of space into a very large space,
驱动力来自一种不可思议的能量
driven by a weird kind of an energy.
我们不知道是何种能量
We're not sure what type of energy
启动了大爆炸
kick-started the Big Bang.
然而不管它是什么 刹那间
But whatever it was, in one brief instant,
它生成了我们宇宙间所有的能量 -
it produced all the energy in our universe--
过去的
past
现在的
present
和将来的
and future.
这是能量最重要 最惊人的一个方面
This is one of the most important and surprising aspects of energy.
在黑洞里
In black holes,
爆发恒星中
exploding stars,
甚至地球上的发电厂里
or even power plants on Earth,
它既不能被创造也不能被消灭
it can be neither created nor destroyed.
它只能从一种形态转换成另一种形态
It can only be transformed from one type to another.
如果宇宙中的物理定律
If the laws of physics in the universe
过去没有改变过 将来也不会改变的话
never changed in the past and don't change in the future,
就没有能力能够被创造或消灭
then no energy can be created or destroyed,
它只能够变形
it can only be transformed.
变形是能量活动的关键
Transformation is the key to how energy works.
宇宙充满了各种能量
The universe is filled with many forms of energy,
如光能
such as light,
声能
sound,
热能
thermal,
化学能
and chemical.
其中最常见的是势能
The most common among them is potential energy,
储存或压抑在物体里的能量
the stored or pent-up energy of an object,
动能 物体的运动
and kinetic energy, the movement of an object.
各式能量
And all forms of energy
都在不停地转换成其它形式的能量
are constantly converted into other forms of energy.
你对准目标开枪时
When you fire a gun at a target,
你可能会认为一旦子弹击中目标
you might think that once the bullet hits the target,
那能量就结束了
that that energy is gone.
但它其实并未结束
But it's not actually gone.
它实际上只是转换成了另一种能量
It's actually just been transformed into another type of energy.
火药里的化学势能
The chemical potential energy in the gunpowder
转换成了子弹的动能
has been converted into the kinetic energy of the bullet,
声波 热量
sound waves, heat,
无论转移到目标什么能量
and whatever energy gets transferred into the target,
都可能使其移动或爆炸
maybe causing it to move or explode.
甚至人体
Even the human body
都是一具经过精调的能量转换机器
is a fine-tuned, energy-transforming machine.
思考我们如何转换能量的一个很好的方式就是吃东西
A good way to think about how we transform energy is eating.
人每天都要吃一定量的卡路里
Humans eat a certain amount of calories every day.
然后不管他们做什么体力活动
And then whatever physical activity they do,
这样就会烧掉那一定量的卡路里
they do that and burn off that certain amount of calories.
你必须继续吃东西 因为你继续活动
And you have to continue to eat because you continue to be active
在烧掉卡路里
and burn off calories.
不可思议的是 爱因斯坦认识到能量与物质
Incredibly, Albert Einstein realized that energy and matter
实际上是同一回事
are really the same thing,
一个可以转换成另一个
and one can be converted into the other.
那就是他的著名的方程式E=mc2的含义
That's the meaning of his famous equation, E=mc squared.
爱因斯坦提出了方法解释了
Einstein came up with a way to explain
这个宇宙间的万物都是能量
that everything in this universe is energy.
物质是能量
Matter is energy.
如果你重 比如 100公斤 那是你的质量
If you weigh, say, 100 kilograms, that's your mass.
如果你将它乘以光速
And if you take that and you multiply that by the speed of light
再乘以光速
and then multiply that by the speed of light,
于是你就得到了你体内的总能量
then you get the amount of energy that exists within your body.
实际上 你体内的能量约1000多倍于
Actually about a thousand times more energy is in your body
人类所爆发过的最大的核弹里的能量
than there was in the largest nuclear weapon detonated by mankind.
物体有可能具有等量的能量
Objects may have the same amount of energy,
但那并不意味着它们具有同样的威力
but that doesn't mean they have the same amount of power.
关键因素在于能量的释放速度
The key ingredient is how quickly the energy is released.
功率等于单位时间里的能量
Power is equal to energy per unit time.
因此即使物体具有很少量的质量
So even something with a really small amount of mass,
比如 这个蛋糕
like, say, this cupcake,
也具有约100万吨TNT的当量
would have the equivalent energy of about a million tons of TNT.
我们都知道蛋糕是不会自我爆发
We all know that cupcakes don't spontaneously explode
释放出100万吨TNT的
and emit a million tons of TNT.
如果我吃了这蛋糕
If I eat a cupcake,
它只是在几个小时里给了我约200大卡
it only gives me about 200 calories of energy over several hours.
反之 如果我有一支炸药
Whereas, if I have a stick of dynamite,
等量的能量会在百万分之一秒里头释放出来
that same amount of energy would be released in, say, a millionth of a second.
所以TNT具有更大的功率
So the TNT has much more power,
尽管它具有等量的能量
even though it has the same amount of energy.
如果你有个批萨 你想吃了那批萨
If you have a pizza and you're going to eat that pizza,
表明你吃下了批萨的1000大卡的值
say you eat a thousand calories worth of pizza.
那可能是很饱饱一餐了
That might be a big meal,
不过你的身体必须将那批萨的质量转换成
but your body has to convert the matter of that pizza
那1000大卡 它真的不那么有效率
into that thousand calories, and it's really not that efficient.
举个例子 TNT或炸药里同样的质量
Take, for example, the same mass in TNT or dynamite.
当你点燃其导火索时 你就会获得更多的能量
When you light the fuse on that, you get way more energy.
我们在地球上所用的所有能量 供养我们人体的
All of the energy we use here on Earth to feed our bodies,
供能给我们电气设备的 点亮我们住宅的
power our electronic devices, and light our homes,
最终都来自外太空
ultimately comes from outer space.
某些最极端的能量转换器
Some of the most extreme transformers of energy
是恒星 包括我们的太阳
are stars, including our Sun.
在任何一秒钟里
At any given second,
太阳都在释放出10的26次方瓦特(能量)
the Sun is putting out about 10-to-the-26 watts.
那可是1后面跟着26个0
That means a 1 with 26 zeros after it.
那就是4000亿颗核弹整个爆发在一秒钟里
That's like 400 billion nuclear weapons all in one second.
就是那么多的能量 我们在一秒钟里从太阳获得的
That's how much energy we're getting from the Sun at any given second.
类似我们太阳的恒星产生出多种能量
Stars like our Sun produce many forms of energy,
但都始于重力
but it all began with gravity.
都是重力意味着我们所观察到的
All gravity means is that we've observed
就是所有的物质落向其它所有的物质
that all matter falls towards all other matter.
有趣的是 你可以用重力
And it's interesting that you can use gravity
来转换能量 一种变为另一种
to transform energy from one type to another.
如果我在这里拿起一块石头 它就具有了一定的势能
If l hold a rock up here, it has a certain potential energy.
然后我将它放开
And then I let it go.
重力就将那势能转换成动能 直到它落地
Gravity turns that potential energy to kinetic energy until it hits the ground.
在130亿年前
Over 13 billion years ago,
重力能将尘埃和气体聚集起来形成了第一代恒星
gravitational energy gathered up dust and gas to form the first stars.
一旦恒星通过重力能形成后
Once a star is formed through gravitational energy,
它就会产生核能
it then produces nuclear energy.
恒星靠核聚变提供动力
Stars are powered by nuclear fusion.
这就是你取多个氢原子
So this is when you take multiple hydrogen atoms
把它们撞击在一起形成更重的元素
and you smash them together to produce heavier elements
如 氦 或碳 氧 氮
like helium or carbon and oxygen and nitrogen.
在这个聚变过程中 巨大的能量
When this fusion process happens, the enormous energy
即所谓的强核力被释放了出来
of what's called the strong nuclear force is liberated,
就是它点亮了恒星
and that is what lights up the star.
我们太阳这样的恒星里头的核聚变
Nuclear fusion within stars like our Sun
产生出一种能量 叫做电磁辐射
then produces a form of energy called electromagnetic radiation.
这些是光子的震荡波
These are oscillating waves of photons,
即光的粒子
or particles of light.
地球上 太空中 电磁辐射
On Earth and in space, electromagnetic radiation
构成了一个能谱
consists of a spectrum of energy.
低端是无线电波
On the low end are radio waves
具有很低的频率 很长的波长
with low frequencies and very long wavelengths.
电磁波谱的高端
On the high end of the electromagnetic spectrum
是伽玛射线 具有很高的频率 极短的波长
are gamma rays with high frequencies and extremely short wavelengths.
电磁辐射的每一个光子
Each photon of electromagnetic radiation
化时15万年
takes up to 150,000 years
才能从太阳的中心走到其表面
to actually get from the center of the Sun to the surface,
然后才能逃逸奔向地球
before it can escape and head towards Earth.
庆幸的是 我们的大气层阻隔了
Luckily for us, our atmosphere blocks
电磁能中的多数有害波长
most of the dangerous wavelengths of electromagnetic energy,
那些紫外线 X射线 伽玛射线
which are ultraviolet, X-rays, and gamma rays,
避免它们来到我们的世界
from reaching our world.
不过它允许可见光 红外线 无线电波通过
But it allows visible light, infrared, and radio waves to pass through.
光能和红外辐射能被陆地和海洋所吸收
Light and infrared energies are absorbed by landmasses and oceans
并转换为热能
and then converted to heat energy.
太阳源源不断发射出电磁辐射
The Sun is continually emitting electromagnetic radiation,
给我们地球上和太空中带来了热能
which is giving us heat energy here on Earth and in space.
人类已找到聪明的办法
Humans have found clever ways
利用宇宙间的能量
to harness the energy of the universe.
我们学会了将太阳辐射转换为热能
We've learned to transform solar radiation into heat
以及电能
as well as electrical energy.
我们利用太阳能所用的最常见的技术之一
One of the most common technologies we use
就是太阳能电池板
to harness the power of sunlight is solar panels.
太阳能电池板通常是用半导体做成的
Solar panels are usually made out of semiconductors
它们是光敏材料
which are light-sensitive.
当阳光照射到硅太阳能电池阵列时
So when sunlight hits the silicon solar array,
它就会产生电荷
it generates charges.
那些电荷会被半导体材料收集起来
Those charges are then swept out of the semiconductor material,
这样就产生了电流
and that generates an electrical current.
电力可以产生于一块太阳能电池
Electricity can be generated from one solar cell
或太阳农场 其中有55万块太阳能电池板
or a solar farm, holding 550,000 solar panels.
那些电流能够提供给方方面面 从住宅
And those currents can charge everything from a home
到时尚的跑车
to a hot sports car.
恒星是了不起的能量转换器
Stars are awesome transformers of energy.
在地球上 我们源源不断地遭遇到
Here on Earth, we're constantly bombarded
以光的形式出现的太阳电磁辐射的轰击
with the Sun's electromagnetic energy in the form of light.
转而 我们将其转换成其他能量
In turn, we convert it into other energies
来驱动我们日常生活中最不可能的东西
to power some of the most unlikely things in our everyday world.
我们今天来到了特斯拉汽车公司来看一下电磁能是如何
We're here at Tesla Motors today to see how electromagnetic energy
被转换成机械能的
can be converted into mechanical energy,
它被用来驱动这台高端跑车
which is used to power this high-end sports car here.
它只需要一般的电源插座里的电力
All it takes is simple electricity from your average wall socket.
我们不妨插上汽车 这个样子
So if we plug the car in, like so,
我们现在就从墙壁插座里获取能量
we're now taking energy from the wall socket,
我们正利用它来充电给汽车电池
and we're using it to charge up the car's battery.
电池 就装在这里
And the battery, located right here,
用来驱动汽车的电机
is used to run the car's electric motor.
车内电脑 就在这里头
So the computer inside the car, which is right here,
能量来自电池
takes energy from the battery
用它来控制单台电机
and uses it to turn the single electric motor,
它驱动的汽车速度惊人 真的
which powers the car at astonishing speeds, actually.
所以你可以想象 你是否想过
So you can imagine, if you had, say,
装在你房顶上的太阳能电池板
solar panels on top of your house
你插在了汽车上
and you were to plug the car in,
你的车实际上是在消耗着阳光
your car would literally be running off of sunlight.
好 我们开路吧
All right, here we go.
将阳光转换成电能有其优越性
And transforming sunlight into electricity has its advantages.
电动车加速快于汽车
Electric vehicles accelerate faster than gas vehicles
因为电机能立刻提供全扭矩
because electric motors provide full torque immediately,
而内燃机得要提速
while gas engines have to rev up.
这台特斯拉能够做到3 9秒内从0到60码
The Tesla here can do zero to 60 in 3.9 seconds,
那就使其快过了
and that makes it faster
这里的任何一台量产的汽油动力车
than just about any other production gasoline-powered car there is.
这就表明了电磁能的强大动力
This just illustrates the great power of electromagnetic energy.
科学不是很好玩吧？
Isn't science fun?
我们的太阳肩负着为我们地球上的一切提供着燃料
Our Sun is responsible for fueling almost everything in our world
一刻不停地将其能量从一种有用的形式转换成另外一种
by transforming its energies from one useful form to yet another.
绿色植物通过光合作用将太阳能转化成化学能
Green plants convert solar energy into chemical energy through photosynthesis,
供养所有的生命 其中包括人类
which feeds all living things, including humans.
我从我的玉米片获取能量 因为谷物
I get energy from my cornflakes, because the corn in the flakes
从阳光的光合作用获得能量
got their energy from photosynthesis of sunlight
将阳光转化成糖 - 碳水化合物
that converts sunlight into sugar-- carbohydrates.
各种分子结合在了分子的原子间
All kinds of molecules have bonds between the atoms in the molecules
这样 它们被打断时 会释放出能量
that, when they break, release energy
给我们运动所需要的能量
and give us the energy that we need when we exercise.
这种能量的生命循环并没有就此结束
And this life cycle of energy doesn't end here.
数百万年里
Over millions of years,
腐烂的动植物的尸体
the decomposed remains of dead plants and animals
被压缩在地下 转化为化石燃料
are compressed underground and converted into fossil fuels.
它们有好多形式 其中有煤炭
They come in many forms, including coal,
石油
petroleum,
和甲烷
and methane.
我们燃烧石油或天然气
When we burn oil or natural gas,
实际上是在释放阳光中的能量
we're really liberating the energy from sunshine
是植物数千 数万
that was collected by plants thousands, tens of thousands,
数十万年里收集的
hundreds of thousands of years ago
储存在地下 形成了化石燃料库
and stored underground in fossil fuel repositories.
化石燃料被认为是不可再生资源
Fossil fuels are considered non-renewable resources.
那并不意味着其能量被完全消灭了
This doesn't mean their energy is completely destroyed,
但是它们无法在短时期内得到自然补充
but that they can't be replenished naturally in a short period of time.
我们讨论到非再生资源
When we talk about non-renewable energy sources,
比如 燃烧化石燃料
like, say, burning fossil fuels,
我们并不是指该能量从宇宙中消失了
we don't mean that energy is gone from the universe.
我们的意思是该能源
What we mean is that that energy source
已经转换成了一种不再有用的形式了
has been transformed into a form that's no longer useful,
比如 废热
like, say, for example, waste heat.
太阳提供了大量我们生存所必需的能量
The Sun provides much of the energy essential for our survival,
不过这个活力充沛的电站也会产生出致命的能量
but this energetic powerhouse can also produce lethal energies.
航天局的斯威夫特太空观测站见证了一个恐怖的事件
NASA's Swift Observatory witnesses a frightening event.
史上观察到的最大的恒星耀斑所释放的能量
The largest stellar flare ever observed releases energy
相当于5000万万亿颗原子弹
equal to 50 million trillion atomic bombs.
致命耀斑发射的X射线形式的能量
The killer flare fires energy in the form of X-rays
会抹去地球上大部分生命
that would obliterate most life on Earth
假如它出自我们的太阳的话
if it came from our Sun.
我们庆幸的是
Fortunately for us,
这种辐射出自飞马座的II Pegasi星
this radiation came from the star II Pegasi,
它在135光年以外
which is 135 light-years away.
即便如此 这一事件表明致命能量
Even so, this incident illustrates the deadly energy
一直被恒星释放出来 包括我们的太阳
being released from stars, including our Sun.
太阳耀斑是巨大的能量相对突然的释放
A solar flare is a relatively sudden release of a tremendous amount of energy.
这种能量来自磁能
This energy comes from magnetic energy.
一团纠缠着的磁场突然释放出这种辐射能
A bunch of tangled magnetic fields suddenly release this radiated energy.
它可以看作是一团拉伸 纠缠的橡皮团
It can be thought of as a bunch of stretched, twisted rubber bands.
那是磁力线
That's the magnetic field lines.
最后 它们突然断裂了
And, eventually, they just snap.
断裂释放出能量 将其从太阳表面
And that snapping releases the energy and channels it outwards
相对局部地方导向外面
from a relatively localized region on the Sun's surface.
太阳耀斑可以达到1500万度
Solar flares can reach as much as 15 million degrees,
因为它将磁能转换成了热能
because it's converting magnetic energy into heat energy
巨大的磁能变成了热能
and massive amounts of magnetic energy into that heat energy.
太阳耀斑在太阳活跃期每天可以发生多次
Solar flares can occur several times a day during high solar activity.
它们爆发时
When they're erupting,
每个耀斑在几分钟里能够产生的能量
each flare can produce as much thermal energy in a few minutes
相当于整个太阳在一秒钟里所产生的能量
as the entire Sun produces in one second.
如果太阳耀斑沉声的一些高能带电粒子
If some of the high-energy charged particles
朝我们而来
generated by solar flares are headed in our direction,
它们就会被另一种能源所偏离 -
they'll be deflected by another energy source,
地球的磁场
the Earth's magnetic field.
它产生于地球熔核中流动的电流
It's produced by electric currents that flow in its molten core.
这些电流有数百英里宽
These currents are hundreds of miles wide
时速数千英里
and move at thousands of miles per hour
跟随着地球的自转
as the Earth rotates.
这个强大的磁场穿过地球
This powerful magnetic field passes through the Earth
进入太空
and enters space.
地球磁场阻止和偏离了
The Earth's magnetic field stops or deflects
大部分来自太阳
most of the charged particles that come at us
或星际太空奔向我们的带电粒子
from the Sun or from interstellar space,
这可是件大好事
and this is a really good thing.
因为它确实对地球生命造成危害
Because it would be really bad for life on Earth
如果大量的这些高能粒子
if a lot of these very high-energy particles
到达地面击中我们的身体的话
made it to the ground and were to hit our bodies.
大质量恒星发出耀斑可以持续上百亿年
A massive star can send off flares for 10 billion years.
恒星的寿终正寝
And when the star nears death,
并不标志着极端能量转换的终结
it doesn't mark the end of the transformation of extreme energy.
事实上 它只是个开端
In fact, it's just the beginning.
一旦你看到恒星诞生了
Once you have the beginning of a star
它启动了核聚变
where it does start the nuclear fusion,
核聚变就会持续下去
then the nuclear fusion continues on,
它就会燃烧直至所有的氢被耗尽 大体上是这样
and it will burn until all the hydrogen is used up, basically.
丧失了核能对其自身的支撑
Deprived of the nuclear energy to support itself,
垂死的巨星终于垮塌了
a massive dying star finally collapses,
引爆了超新星爆发
igniting a supernova explosion.
超新星辐射的能量
A supernova can radiate as much energy as
相当于太阳毕生所发出的能量
the Sun will emit over its entire life span.
恒星的生存 在于其内部核熔炉发出的能量与
Stars exist in a balance between energy from a nuclear furnace on the inside
其全部质量的重力引起自身垮塌之间的平衡
and gravitational pull of all the mass of it collapsing in on itself.
在某些时刻 核熔炉开始消失
And at some point when the nuclear furnace starts to die out,
重力吸引成为了那场战争的最后赢家
gravitational attraction becomes the final winner of that conflict.
它垮塌了 发出一束光芒
It collapses, and it emits a bunch of light,
那是因为重力压垮了恒星内部的核熔炉
and it's due to gravity overcoming the nuclear furnace in the star.
现在重要的是要记住
Now, it's important to keep in mind
爆发恒星的能量并不是无中生有创造出来的
that the energy of an exploding star isn't simply created out of nothing.
那是能量再次从一种形态转换成了另一种形态
Again, it's energy that's transformed from one type to another.
大质量恒星的星核垮塌了
The core of a massive star collapses,
释放出大量的重力势能
releasing a lot of gravitational potential energy.
那能量于是就送出为中微子
That energy then is channeled into neutrinos,
成为喷射物质的动能
into the kinetic energy of the ejected material,
成为我们看得见的能量
and into the visible energy that we observe.
超新星是太空中最具爆炸性的能量转换器之一
Supernovas are one of the most explosive transformers of energy in space.
然而 超新星所释放的99%的能量
However, 99% of the energy released during a supernova
都被转换成肉眼其实看不见的东西 -
is converted into something that's actually invisible to the naked eye--
怪异 幽灵般的粒子 叫做中微子
strange, ghostly particles called neutrinos.
中微子是几乎没有质量的高能粒子
Neutrinos are nearly massless energetic particles
移动速度几近光速
that move at almost the speed of light
穿透物体几乎畅通无阻
and pass through matter virtually undisturbed.
每一秒钟 有超过50万亿个太阳中微子
Every second, more than 50 trillion solar neutrinos
穿越过人体 而我们却毫不知晓
pass through the human body without us knowing it.
其中的一个与你体内的粒子互动的可能性
The likelihood of one of them interacting
非常低 以至于你并未察觉
with a particle in your body is so low that you don't notice it.
即使发生这样的情况
And even if it did happen,
也只是你身体所获得的一丁点的能量
it would be just a little blip of energy that your body gets,
它远比不上
which is much less significant
身体所获得的其他所有的能量
than all the other blips of energy it gets
那些出自闯入你身体的其他各种粒子
from other kinds of particles that are running into you,
如光或辐射
such as light or radiation
那是地球自然产生出来的
that's naturally produced from the Earth.
中微子一度曾无法检测到
Neutrinos were once impossible to detect.
它们穿过地球
They traveled right through the Earth
又悄无声息地退回太空
and exited back into space unnoticed.
不过在日本飞騨 3000多英尺的地下
But in Hida, Japan, over 3,000 feet underground,
安装有超级神冈探测器
lives the Super-K Observatory.
它安置了一只巨大的不锈钢罐
It houses a massive stainless steel tank
里面是超纯水
containing ultra-pure water.
当中微子与水中的电子或原子核发生作用时
It's been discovered that when neutrinos interact
就会被发现
with the electrons or atomic nuclei in water,
它们会生成带电的粒子
they produce a charged particle
发出一道紫外线
which creates a flash of ultraviolet light.
粒子流进入水中时
As that particle streams through the water,
实际上会发出一丝辐射
it actually gives out a tiny blip of radiation
能被那些小小的光探测器测到
that can be measured by those little light detectors,
于是就表明 那就是中微子
which then says, that's a neutrino.
那些幽灵般的粒子能否成为地球上的能源呢？
Could these stealthy particles be a source of energy here on Earth?
那是伊利诺伊州芝加哥的艾伦
That's what Alan K. From Chicago, Illinois,
想问《宇宙》节目的问题
wanted to ask "The Universe,"
他发短信给我们
so he texted us:
我们如何能利用太阳发出的中微子能呢？
How can we harness energy from neutrinos emitted by the sun?
有趣的问题 艾伦
Interesting question, Alan.
事实证明中微子实在是难以发现
It turns out that neutrinos are incredibly hard to detect.
因此我们可能无法利用太阳的中微子能
So we probably can't harness the Sun's neutrino energy.
此外 我们真的不想这么做
Also we don't really want to,
因为只有约3%的太阳能
because only about 3% of the Sun's energy
表现为中微子形态
is in the form of neutrinos.
更加便当地是利用阳光
It's much easier to harness the sunlight,
那要多得多了
and there's much more of it.
中微子可能不能够缓解我们的能源危机
Neutrinos may not be able to alleviate our energy crisis,
但每一个星系里都蛰伏着一个贪婪的怪兽
but lurking in each galaxy exists a ravenous beast
那就有可能成为外太空里最节能的引擎了
that just may be the most fuel-efficient engine in outer space.
能量能从一种形态转换成另一种形态的能力
The ability to convert energy from one form to another
激发了未来太空殖民的创新理念
has inspired innovative ideas for future space colonization.
超大质量黑洞
Supermassive black holes
驻扎在大多数星系的中心
reside in the centers of most galaxies,
其中包括我们的银河系
including our Milky Way.
它们可以储存和释放数十亿颗超新星的能量
They can store and unleash the energy of billions of supernovas.
超大质量黑洞形成时
When the supermassive black holes were forming,
巨量的重力势能
a tremendous amount of gravitational potential energy
转换成了光辐射和其他形式的能量
was converted into radiated light and other forms of energy.
因为你有大量的物质被压缩进了一个很小的体积里
'Cause you had a lot of material get compressed into a very small volume.
它就不得不放弃大量的能量
It had to give up a lot of energy.
一个超大质量黑洞是100亿个太阳的量
A supermassive black hole is 10 billion Suns' worth.
那意味着它相当于100亿个太阳的质量
That means it has the equivalent mass of 10 billion stars,
整个被装进了一个很小的空间里
just all packed into a very tiny space.
航天局的钱德拉X射线望远镜揭示了一个费解的谜团
NASA's Chandra X-ray Telescope unravels a puzzling mystery
黑洞所产生的转换能量
about the transformational energies produced by a black hole.
它发现超大质量黑洞
It detects a supermassive black hole's
强大的重力能在拽拉着附近的恒星
powerful gravitational energy drawing in a nearby star.
贪婪巨兽吞噬着恒星时 旋转疯狂
As the gluttonous beast gorges on the star, it spins wildly,
有时会接近光速
sometimes approaching the speed of light.
这种动能将气体和碎片卷入洞内
This kinetic energy twists up the gas and debris falling into the hole
形成了飞速旋转的旋转吸积盘
to form a fast-spinning rotational accretion disk.
这种旋转的物质就以强大的喷射释放出来
This rotating material is then released in powerful jets.
这种极端的高能物质飞旋在黑洞边
This extremely high-energy material spiraling around the black hole
形成了极强的磁场
creates a very large magnetic field.
现在 一些物质
Now, some of the material
实际上是沿着那些磁力线
actually follows those magnetic field lines
沿着它们射出来 形成了强大的喷射
and gets shot out along them, forming a big, powerful jet
好象是喷枪那样
that's sort of like a blowtorch.
最近的计算机模拟显示出
Recent computer simulations have shown
如果黑洞旋转形成的极端的动能或转动能
that if the extreme kinetic or rotational energy
能够利用的话
from a black hole's spin could be harnessed,
这些黑色巨兽
these black monsters
就有可能成为终极星系电池
could become the ultimate galactic batteries.
如果你能有一个飞旋的黑洞盘旋在那里
Wouldn't it be great if you could have a spinning black hole
就在太空中 那不是很伟大吗？
just spinning there, out there in space?
你把这东西安放在它周围
And you build this thing in orbit round it
从中提取能量
that extracts energy from that,
将会给你巨大的能量
and that would give you a huge amount of energy
为你的超级先进的文明提供燃料
to fuel your super-advanced civilization.
黑洞有可能不只是负责
And black holes may not only be responsible
产生各种能量
for generating different forms of energies.
它们可能还承担起作为星系回收中心的双重作用
They may serve a dual purpose as a galactic recycling center.
可以想象一个先进的文明
One might imagine an advanced civilization
居住在飞旋的黑洞旁边的景象
living near a spinning black hole.
它可能会将垃圾车靠近飞旋的黑洞
It could send garbage trucks close to the spinning black hole
在适当的时候倾倒它们的垃圾
that would dump their garbage at the appropriate time.
然后那些垃圾车会挣扎出黑洞
Those trucks would then emerge from the vicinity of the black hole
带着动能 飞进去
with more energy of motion, kinetic energy, than they had going in.
那些车辆于是会发动涡轮机 像风车那样
Those trucks could then hit a turbine, like a windmill,
驱动涡轮机 产生电能
drive the turbine, generate electrical energy,
从而点亮他们的城市
and thus light up their cities.
多么利索的办法 既扔掉了你的垃圾
What a neat way to get rid of your garbage
又同时解决了你的能源危机
and solve your energy crisis all at the same time.
黑洞可能会供能给未来的太空移民
Black holes may energize a future space colony.
但是科学家现在发现
But scientists are now discovering
飞旋黑洞产生的能量
that the energy from whirling black holes
有可能转换成某种危害
may be transforming into something dangerous.
宇宙射线是高能带电粒子
Cosmic rays are highly energetic charged particles.
与其名字相背 它们并不是光能射线
Contrary to their name, they're not rays of light energy.
相反 它们带有巨大的动能
Rather, they contain very large amounts of kinetic energy,
会导致致命的结果
which can cause deadly effects.
宇宙射线的能量远大于
Cosmic rays are way more energetic
我们在地球上所能产生的任何东西
than anything we've been able to produce on Earth,
有数十万倍的能量
hundreds of thousands of times more energetic.
最具能量的宇宙射线
The most energetic cosmic rays
叫做超高能宇宙射线
are called ultra-high energy cosmic rays.
其速度接近光速
They travel at close to the speed of light
具有不断增强的亮度
with ever-Increasing brightness.
超高能宇宙射线具有的能量相当于
An ultra-high energy cosmic ray has about as much energy
时速100英里击出的网球
as a tennis ball hit at 100 miles an hour.
那是专业选手在球场上击出的速度
That's how fast the professionals get them going on court.
那听上去好像并没有很多能量
That doesn't sound like a lot of energy,
但实际上有数以万亿计的粒子
but actually there are trillions of particles
构成了这个特定的网球
making up a given tennis ball.
所发生的是你将所有的能量
And what's going on is that you've taken all of that energy
放入了一个亚原子粒子里
and put it into one subatomic particle,
那就是宇宙射线闯入我们大气层的情形
and that's what a cosmic ray coming in through our atmosphere is like.
所以那就是单个粒子具有大量能量的原因所在
And so that's a lot of energy for a single particle to have.
新的证据表明 以活跃的星系核闻名的星系
New evidence suggests that galaxies known as active galactic nuclei
可能是这些超高能宇宙射线的源头
may be the source for these ultra-high energy cosmic rays.
这些星系有超高速旋转的
These are galaxies that have super spinning
超大质量黑洞在其中心
supermassive black holes at their cores.
那些基本上就是极端强大的能量转换器
Those are essentially extremely powerful generators of energy.
磁场和电场飞旋
There are magnetic fields and electric fields all spinning around
以极高的速度抛出粒子
and throwing out particles at incredibly high rates,
通常都是产生于其中心的超大质量黑洞
usually generated by a supermassive black hole at the core.
那种系统 尤其是黑洞
And that sort of system, black holes especially,
能够产生巨大的能量
are able to produce huge amounts of energy
能够将这些粒子抛向四面八方
that can throw out these particles in all directions.
超高能宇宙射线
Ultra high-energy cosmic rays
已经构成了对星际旅行的头号健康威胁之一
have become one of the top health threats to interplanetary space missions.
这些带电粒子会洞穿宇宙飞船
These charged particles could hurtle right through a spaceship
像小导弹那样击中宇航员
and penetrate astronauts like tiny ballistic missiles,
撕裂DNA分子 甚至杀死细胞
ripping apart DNA molecules and even killing cells.
超高能宇宙射线 如果它作用于人体组织
A high-energy cosmic ray, if it interacts with human tissue,
会损伤组织中的DNA
can do damage to the DNA in that tissue
导致细胞的破坏 甚至导致癌症
and lead to a disruption of the cell, maybe leading to cancer.
宇宙射线可能不仅仅威胁到太空旅行者
And cosmic rays may not only threaten space travelers.
分分秒秒 宇宙射线都在轰击我们地球的大气层
Every second, cosmic rays bombard our Earth's atmosphere.
有些甚至一路关关斩将
Some even penetrate all the way through
落在我们星球上
and rain down on our planet.
宇宙射线转换能量的关键在于速度
The key to cosmic rays' transformational energy is speed.
因此即使它只有极小的质量 比如大多数宇宙射线
So even if it has really tiny mass, like most cosmic rays,
但它们都已经获得了巨大的速度
they've got enormous velocity.
因此它们的动能可是非常之大
So their kinetic energy can be really, really large.
它们闯入地球的大气层时
When they strike the Earth's atmosphere,
会与大气分子碰撞 主要是氧和氮
they collide with molecules, mainly oxygen and nitrogen.
这就产生了紫外线形态的能量风暴
This produces a storm of energy in the form of ultraviolet radiation
倾泻到我们的星球上
that cascades down on our planet.
那些宇宙射线始终不停地从外太空闯入
Those cosmic rays are coming from outer space all the time,
昼夜不停
24 hours a day,
扑向外层大气 撞击大气分子
just impinging upon the outer atmosphere and running into the air molecules,
所产生的大量粒子
then producing showers of particles
我们可以在地球表面检测到
that we can detect here on the surface of the Earth.
所幸的是 超高能宇宙射线
Fortunately for us, one original ultra-high energy cosmic ray
将其能量分散给了数百万乃至数十亿个粒子
spreads its energy out to millions or even billions of particles.
因此其能量
So its energy,
以原本的X射线以及伽玛射线形态出现的
originally in the form of X-rays and gamma rays,
已经消散 已不再对人类有害了
is so dissipated that it's no longer harmful to humans.
然而 这些宇宙射线
However, these cosmic rays
会阻断你的手机通话
could cut off your cell phone conversation.
这些空气簇射 如它们的名称那样
These air showers, as they're called,
产生于撞击外层大气的宇宙射线
which are produced by the cosmic rays hitting the outer atmosphere,
会影响到地面上的电子设备
those could affect electronics here on the ground.
我们的电脑和手机
Our computers and cell phones
以及我们每天都是用的其它设备
and other devices that we use every day
正变得越来越脆弱
are becoming more and more delicate
因为我们的电路小型化了
as we miniaturize our circuitry,
那就使其越发对宇宙射线的干扰敏感了
and that actually makes it much more sensitive to being disrupted by cosmic rays.
遍及整个宇宙
In every corner of the universe,
我们目击了能量在运动中的破坏性
we witness the destructive nature of energy in motion.
然而 在地球上
Yet, here on Earth,
我们生成了一种独特的能量
we generate a unique form of energy
它产生于太阳系诞生的时候
that comes from the creation of our solar system.
自时间诞生以来
Since the beginning of time,
能量就一直是宇宙间永恒的魔术表演
energy has been the universe's long-standing magic act,
持续不断地从一种形态转变成另一种形态
constantly changing from one form to another.
一种独特的极端能源
One unique type of extreme energy
就是我们太阳系诞生时的遗产
is the legacy of our solar system's creation.
地热能
Geothermal energy
来自地球岩核所产生的热量
comes from the heat created in the Earth's rocky core,
它存在于地表下方约4000英里处
which exists about 4,000 miles below the surface.
我们的太阳系最早形成于约45亿年前
Our solar system was first formed about 4 1/2 billion years ago,
当时气体及尘埃云凝聚成了
when a cloud of gas and dust condensed
太阳及所有的行星
to form the Sun and all of the planets.
小部分气体和尘埃
A small fraction of that gas and dust
由铀-238和钍之类的放射性元素构成
consists of radioactive elements like uranium-238 and thorium.
地球凝结时 其中一些放射性元素
When the Earth condensed, some of those radioactive elements
积聚在了我们地球的内部
got collected into our Earth's interior.
在那些元素数十亿年的缓慢衰变中
As those elements slowly decay over billions of years,
它们加热了地球的内部
they heat up the interior of the Earth.
我们可以通过地热能获得这个热能
We can access this heat energy as geothermal energy.
地表的某些区域
Some areas of the Earth's surface
让这种地热能渗出
allow this geothermal energy to seep through,
诸如靠近板块构造的边缘
such as near plate tectonic boundaries,
火山 间歇泉
volcanoes, and geysers.
地热能能够在板块构造边缘附近得到利用
Geothermal energy can be tapped near plate tectonic boundaries
在那里 这种冒出的热液
where this hot stuff comes up,
是很久以前爆发恒星所产生的
produced by exploding stars long ago
具有放射性 释放它们的能量
that are radioactive and release their energy
历经了数十亿年的时间
over time scales of billions of years.
世界各地的地热发电厂
Geothermal plants around the world
利用过热水库里的热能来产生电能
harness heat energy from superheated reservoirs to create electrical energy.
来看它的工作原理
Here's how it works.
高温高压水送到地表
High-temperature, high-pressure water is brought to the surface,
进入低压室 喷成蒸汽
where it enters a low-pressure chamber and flashes into steam.
这个蒸汽所产生的压力输送给涡轮机
The pressure created by this steam is channeled through a turbine,
使其旋转产生电力
which spins to generate electrical power.
一旦蒸汽离开涡轮机
Once the steam has exited the turbine,
它或者被释放进大气中成为水蒸汽
it is either released into the atmosphere as water vapor,
或者冷却变回液态水
or it cools back into liquid water
被注回地下
and is injected back underground.
直到最近几乎所有的实例中 地热发电场
In almost all cases until recently, geothermal power plants
都要么就是在板块的边缘附近
have been either near plate boundaries
要么是在地壳的热点 薄弱点
or hotspots, weak spots in the Earth's crust
那里会有炙热的岩浆冒出
through which the hot magma can come.
由于地表的大部分并不靠近板块边缘
So since most of the Earth's surface is not near a plate boundary,
因此利用地热能相对较为困难
it's been relatively difficult to tap into geothermal energy.
最佳含量和质量的地热能
The best concentration and quality of geothermal energy
存在于高水平的板块和火山活跃的地方
exists where there are high levels of tectonic and volcanic activity,
比如火环 它环绕着太平洋
like the Ring of Fire, which circles the Pacific Ocean.
但靠近板块边缘采掘是棘手的事情
But excavating close to plate boundaries is tricky.
为了从地球的地热能中获得大量的可消耗能源
To get a lot of consumer energy out of the geothermal energy of the Earth
确实需要入地深入到
really requires digging quite deep
温度足够高的地方
to where the temperatures are high enough
你才能获得大量的能源
that you get a lot of energy out.
提取地热能
The technological challenges
供消费者使用的技术挑战十分巨大
for extracting geothermal energy for consumer use are huge.
你需要或者去驾驭火山
You either need to harness a volcano
或者就是钻入地球非常非常的深
or drill down very, very deep into the Earth,
或者去盖住黄石公园里的间歇泉
or cap the geysers at Yellowstone.
不过此类地热能可能并非地球独享
But this type of thermal energy may not be exclusive to planet Earth.
木卫一 木星的四颗主要的卫星之一
Io, one of Jupiter's four main moons,
有活火山活动 和地球一样
has active volcanism, like Earth.
但是其核心的地热能的产生
But the thermal energy from its core is produced
并非通过放射性元素的衰变
not through the decay of radioactive elements,
而是通过潮汐加热
but rather through tidal heating.
木卫一有一个环绕木星的椭圆轨道
lo has an elliptical orbit around Jupiter,
因此有时它会比其他时候更加接近木星
so sometimes it's closer to Jupiter than at other times.
当它靠近木星时
When it's closer to Jupiter,
木卫一的潮汐牵引要大于它远离木星时
the tidal stretching of Io is greater than when it's farther from Jupiter.
因此在其环绕木星过程中 木卫一好像在来回挤压
So as it orbits Jupiter, Io sort of squishes back and forth.
那就引起了内部岩石的大量摩擦
That gives rise to a lot of rubbing of the interior rocks,
于是它们就释放出能量
and they then release energy.
内部变热
The interior gets hot,
岩浆流向地表
magma flows to the surface,
你就看到大量的喷发火山
and you see a bunch of erupting volcanoes.
因而那可以被认为是地热能
So that can be thought of as a geothermal energy.
我们当然知道木星的卫星木卫一内部
We certainly know that the inside of Jupiter's moon, Io,
是融化的 因为我们看到有火山存在
is molten because we see volcanoes there,
那是地热的相等物
and that is the equivalent of geothermal.
我之所以说相等物 是因为geo意指地球
I say equivalent because "geo" means "earth."
因此严格说来 地热是地球内部的能量
So, strictly speaking, geothermal is Earth's interior energy.
木星有可能并不具有其卫星木卫一那样的熔核
Planet Jupiter may not have a molten core like its moon Io.
不过气体巨星炙热的内部
But the gas giant's hot interior
会产生另一种极端能量 - 风
generates another form of extreme energy--wind.
行星巨人 木星和土星
The giant planets, Jupiter and Saturn,
都具有狂风大作的大气层
have very windy atmospheres.
它们暴风肆虐
They are very stormy,
不只是因为来自太阳的热量
not just because of heat from the Sun,
而实际上主要是源于其内部产生的热量
but, in fact, largely because of heat generated on the inside.
其内部还在收缩
Their interior parts are still contracting,
释放出重力能
releasing gravitational energy,
并转换成大气的动能 -
and converting it into energy of motion of the atmosphere--
大风和风暴
winds and storms.
这是又一例
This is another example
能量从一种形态转换成另一种形态
of the conversion of one form of energy into another.
这些巨星上的一些风可以有巨大的风速
Some of the winds on the giant planets can travel at immense speeds,
时速600甚至700英里
600 or even 700 miles per hour.
现在 其中多数只有每小时几百英里
Now, most of them are only a few hundred miles per hour,
但它依然超过了地球上的大风暴
which still is big compared to even big storms on Earth.
然而最快的风暴可以时速达到600或700英里
But the fastest storms can travel at 600 or 700 miles per hour.
那确实够快的
That's really fast.
地球也受惠于风能
Earth also benefits from wind energy,
但它并不源自其核心
but its source doesn't come from its core,
而相反 是直接来自太空
but rather, directly from space.
我们在地球上所见到的风能的来源
The source of energy that we see in winds on Earth
实际上是太阳的加热
is really solar heating.
太阳以不同的量加热大气层的不同部分
The sun heats different parts of the atmosphere by different amounts,
那就导致了失衡 使空气产生了流动
and that causes imbalances that allow the air to flow.
风能 就是机械能
That's wind energy, mechanical energy
来自太阳的电磁能
coming from the Sun's electromagnetic energy.
风能能够被用来驱动涡轮机
That wind energy can then be used to drive a turbine,
将其转换成电能 点亮我们的城市
converting it into electrical energy that lights our cities.
能量推动了宇宙的演化
Energy has propelled the evolution of the universe
自其在130多亿年前诞生伊始
since its birth over 13 billion years ago.
然而现在科学家发现了一种神秘的能量
But now science has discovered a mysterious type of energy
那可能就是宇宙死神
that just may be the cosmic grim reaper.
整个太空中存在着一个幽灵能量
Throughout outer space exists a phantom energy.
我们不知道这个神秘的东西是何方神圣
We don't know where this mysterious form originated,
但现在被认为它会毁灭地球的生命
but it's now believed that it could destroy life on Earth,
甚至宇宙本身
and maybe even the universe itself.
上世纪90年代 天文学家利用哈勃太空望远镜
In the 1990s, astronomers used the Hubble Space Telescope
及其它观手段来测量其它星系里的
and other observatories to measure the distances of exploding stars
爆炸恒星之间的距离
in other galaxies.
让他们震惊不已的是 他们注意到非常奇特的东西
To their shock, they noticed something quite peculiar.
最近 天文学家通过观察超新星的距离发现了
Recently, astronomers have discovered by looking at the distances of supernovae
宇宙实际上在加速分开
that the universe is actually accelerating apart.
它不光在膨胀 而且实际上还在加速
It's not just expanding, but it's actually accelerating.
某种神秘的能量正驱动宇宙分开 越来越快
Some mysterious energy is driving the universe apart faster and faster.
天文学家意识到宇宙的膨胀
Astronomers realized that the expansion of the universe
一直加速不停是缘自暗能量
is speeding up with time due to dark energy,
一种无处不在的怪异的能量形式
a strange form of energy that exists everywhere.
它占据了宇宙间近75%的物质和能量
It accounts for almost 75% of all mass and energy in the universe.
它是宇宙一大谜团
It is one of the big mysteries of the universe.
事实上 某种意义上它是宇宙最大的谜团
It is, in fact, the biggest mystery of the universe in some sense,
因为暗能量是宇宙能量预算中最大的组成部分
because dark energy is the largest component of the energy budget of the universe.
我们目前的知识和对暗能量的了解
Our current knowledge and understanding of dark energy
是十分有限的 尽管暗能量
is very limited, even though dark energy
囊括了宇宙中近75%的物质和能量
comprises almost 75% of all matter and energy in the universe.
这非常类似于我们
It would be similar to us
只探索了地球的陆地
having only explored the landmass on the Earth
而海洋却覆盖了地球整个表面的近75%
when the ocean comprises almost 75% of all of the surface of Earth.
我们现在才刚开始探索暗能量
We are just now starting to explore dark energy.
科学家曾以为引力
Scientists had once thought that gravitational attraction
会促使宇宙的膨胀
would cause the expansion of the universe
随着时间的推移而减慢
to slow down with time.
他们相信宇宙从大爆炸开始一直在膨胀
The belief was that the universe was expanding from the Big Bang
引力应当会减慢膨胀的速度
and that gravity ought to be slowing that expansion rate.
当时的大疑问是
And the big question at that time was,
引力是否强大到足以将万物拉回到一起？
is gravity strong enough to pull everything back together?
但我们得到了一个惊奇
But we got a surprise.
引力并没有减缓膨胀
Gravity wasn't slowing down the expansion.
事实上 我们仔细观察后
In fact, when we observed carefully,
发现膨胀仍在加速
we discovered that the expansion was accelerating.
虽然引力束缚了行星 恒星 星系
While gravity binds planets, stars, and galaxies,
但暗能量似乎在拉伸时空结构
dark energy appears to stretch the fabric of space and time,
从而将星系推开
thereby pushing galaxies apart.
最近的观察表明暗能量
Recent observations have shown that dark energy
正导致我们的宇宙的膨胀 达到了前所未有的速度
is causing our universe to expand at an ever faster pace.
在宇宙的历史长河中
Over the history of the universe,
暗能量的量是相对固定的
the relative amounts of dark energy
而引力作用的物质和能量却发生了改变
and regular, gravitationally attractive matter and energy have changed.
早期 很正常 引力能占主导
Early on, regular, gravitationally attractive energy dominated,
那是因为物体靠在了一起
and that's because objects were close together.
它们之间并没有太多的暗能量
There wasn't much dark energy in between them,
因此其累积效应还很小
so its cumulative effect was very small.
但随着宇宙的膨胀
But as the universe expanded
星系之间相互远离
and galaxies got farther apart from each other,
太空中的量
the amount of space,
充斥各处的暗物质 增多了
all of which was filled with dark energy, increased.
来把我们的宇宙模型假设为
Let's suppose we model the universe
一块不断膨胀的葡萄干面包
as an expanding loaf of raisin bread,
其中葡萄干就是星系 -
where the raisins are the galaxies--
它们不会膨胀 -
they don't expand--
面团则均匀地分布着酵母
and the dough is uniformly filled with yeast.
那就像是暗能量
That's like the dark energy.
现在来假设我们继续把酵母投入到
Now suppose we continue to inject yeast
烘烤中的面包使其膨胀
into the baking bread as it expands.
它会随着时间推移膨胀得越来越快 因为有了越来越多的酵母
It'll expand faster and faster with time, 'cause there's more and more yeast.
它会加速其膨胀
It'll be accelerating in its expansion.
同样 随着时间的推移
In a similar way, with time,
宇宙的暗能量越来越多
there's more and more dark energy in the universe,
结果 加速 加快了它的膨胀
thus, accelerating, speeding up its expansion.
如果暗能量继续加速我们宇宙的膨胀
If dark energy continues to speed up the expansion of our universe,
我们将会最终遭遇到大寒冻
we could eventually experience the big chill.
星系团会扩展得越来越稀疏
Clusters of galaxies will spread thinner and thinner.
星系将会耗尽其气体补给去形成新的恒星
Galaxies will exhaust their gas supply to form new stars
而老的恒星则会熄灭
and old stars will burn out.
宇宙会变得暗无天日 寒不可耐
The universe will become dark and insufferably cold.
在一个膨胀永无止境 或几近永无止境的宇宙中
In a universe that expands forever, or nearly forever,
最终太阳及所有的恒星都将熄灭
eventually the Sun and all the other stars will burn out.
它们用尽了自己的核燃料
They'll use up their nuclear fuel.
到了那时 基本上已没有能源供地球上的生命了
At that point, there will be basically no source of energy for life on Earth.
因此生命据我们所料 将不复存在
So life as we know it will cease to exist.
但要是这种严酷的情景一旦发生
But if this grim scenario happens,
宇宙间的所有能量将消失殆尽
all the energy in the universe won't disappear,
因为我们的能量预算在大爆炸开始时就已经排定
because our energy budget has been fixed since the Big Bang.
不管怎样 能量将会变得无法使用
However, the energy will become impossible to access.
能量变得极其分散 被稀释到那样的程度
The energy gets spread out so much and diluted to such an extent
将不再可用
that it is no longer usable.
但也有关于宇宙能量命运的其他理论
But there are other theories about the fate of our universe's energy.
在遥远的未来 有人提出
In the distant future, some propose
能量会被转移到另外的地方
energy could be transferred to another place,
没准另一个宇宙
perhaps another universe.
根据物理定律 能量不能被创造或消灭
According to the laws of physics, energy can't be created or destroyed.
所有能量 在我们宇宙中的
And all the energy that is within our universe
一直就存在 还将一直存在
has always been here and will always be here.
但要是有虫洞或什么东西打开了平行宇宙
But what if a wormhole or something opens up to a parallel universe
流走了其中的一些能量会怎么样呢？
and bleeds off some of that energy?
有可能我们的宇宙会开始冷却
It's possible that our universe would start cooling off,
因为我们在那一点上渗漏
because we're leaking at that point.
我不认为那是个好主意
And I don't think that would be a good idea,
因为最终宇宙会冷却
because eventually the universe would cool off
到一切都被冻结的地步
to a point where everything would freeze out
生命将对此无法承受
and life wouldn't be able to withstand that.
我们不知道遥远的未来将如何把握
We don't know what the far future holds
我们的宇宙里乃至更远的能量
for energy in our universe or beyond.
不过眼下
But for the time being,
它依然是我们宇宙中激情四射 不断变化的组成部分
it remains the violent yet vital and ever-changing component